<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-18T01:12:07+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/</id><title type="html">Kyle Alan Hale</title><subtitle>Some writing, some pictures, &amp;c.</subtitle><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Cottonwood Tree</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/the-cottonwood-tree" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Cottonwood Tree" /><published>2017-08-20T18:19:01+00:00</published><updated>2017-08-20T18:19:01+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/the-cottonwood-tree</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/the-cottonwood-tree">&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IyIUTtlFha4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metaphors aren’t hard to come by when you’ve pulled down more of a tree than you meant, but they feel even closer when you’re the one who chose the spot to affix the chain, and then affixed it. I could really dig into those metaphors, compare them to my own slash-and-burn history, my tendency to break things open in order to know how they got put together, to hurt when I mean to heal, but right now I just want to talk about the tree.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know it’s always been there. The family house was built in 1905, and the tree can’t have come along much later. I don’t know when it was born, but by the time I was, it was already massive. My first empathized tree-pain was when a branch fell off during a storm, almost hitting someone, and I wonder if the general worry directed at the person was sublimated into my empathy for the tree. I felt it again some time later when half the tree had to be excised to meet power line regulations. It always adjusted, filled out, retained its grandeur, and I marked my life by its presence like I did with the stars, the east mountains, and my parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climbing it was a challenge. My brothers and I climbed all the trees that could hold our weight, but this tree was something different. You could get lost just climbing the folds of its bark at the base. The nearest branch was as big as any of the other trees, and it was a dozen feet up. We managed to find ways to get up there every once in a while, but it was like going through all the work to climb the beanstalk and only finding more beanstalk. It gave you the feeling that if you could climb long enough there was something to find up there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than one plan for a house-sized treehouse was half-drawn-up. My imagination outpaced my ability to draft plans, let alone execute them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was very young we lived across the lot in a trailer house, and I fell in love with a cat I named Charcoal. I first saw it between the cottonwood and the tall Lombardy across from it, a tree deserving its own memorial. The last time I saw the cat I had left a family gathering to follow it around the back of the old house next door, the one I knew had been a brick house when my grandpa had lived there as a child, the one that was sold out of the family sometime in the vague past, to be stuccoed and wainscoted and orange-tiled and abandoned until my parents would buy and renovate it years later so that I could be sitting in it right now, and the cat disappeared through a gap in the brick foundation. For months I looked for it at that spot, and for years I thought of it when I walked by. Now it’s hidden by the house’s addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stole a knife from my grandpa and buried it at the base of the tree so that I could dig it up later and claim I found it, and keep it. I never found it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before my grandpa died the land behind the cottonwood was what we called “the rock yard”, a landing for semi-trucks fresh from the rock quarries and diesel tankers filling up the barrels of my grandpa’s fuel supply. In the summertime as the sun set and the diesel drums cooled, they would contract with a bang. My bedroom window faced them, and I fell asleep to the crickets and the report of those barrels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He would also gather stone from the hillsides, “float stone” he called it, and when he’d get back he would unload the stone from the back of his rock truck, a late 70s Ford with a diamond-plate bed, with which I would really learn to drive the summer after I got my driver’s license by heading up to pick float stone with my cousin, still pretty much the same five-year-old sitting in the cab eating the rest of my grandpa’s Vienna sausages while I watched him stack the green-lichened purple flagstones into tidy pallets in the shade of the cottonwood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used to gather up its cotton in piles and make plans to card and spin it into underwear. The cotton would get everywhere; sometimes it looked like it had snowed in the summer. We once dug a small pit and lined its inside with the cotton and its surface with cottonwood branches, leaves, and dirt: a trap, and I don’t know if we used it on anyone back then, but I’ve been told the trick was repeated later and caught me while walking around outside with a bowl full of cereal, which got upset, but I don’t remember if I did, because I don’t remember it happening at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t remember a lot. A couple of my high school years must have been very eventful, but all I can recall without checking my journal or asking my mom is lots of Pearl Jam, computer parts, and Tolkien appendices. Aside from that, a deep, terrifying, comforting, overwhelming darkness. I don’t know how to describe my discovery of depression without sounding emo, which is all the wrong impression to give, because I was devoted to grunge, although I didn’t even hear that word until the end of the 90s, and I disapproved, because the music was sacred to me. At the time, to me, grunge was just what music was. You could keep your studio, glimmering, popular hits; I wanted it raw and immediate. I mean that didn’t keep me from singing “wasn’t me,” and later I’d spend time as a producer and recording engineer and find out that even the rawness was carefully prepared, but the sensation of immediacy was important to me. It was more than music; it was medication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was always a writer, but I started writing music because words weren’t enough. Now I pile words on top of words because nothing is enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point as I tried to figure out why existence was such a heavy thing for me when it didn’t seem to be for others, I grew to suspect that I didn’t just feel pain more deeply, but that I also felt beauty and love more deeply. There’s a danger in this line of thought; it can lead to the implication that that others feel less of those things, or reinforce the morbid fallacy that pain should be glorified. It’s easy to debate claims of a correlation between creative output and depression/anxiety/mania/altogether messiness, and I’ll do some of that in a bit, but to be honest at times I’ve needed the seeds of hope that these ideas offer in the face of despair. I’ve needed something to balance out the social stigma tied to that mess. I’ve needed to be able to see my particular emotional balance as a wholeness, an asset, that no one is right but at least I am not wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep thinking that I could have climbed up higher, could have twisted the dead branch out from another angle, and saved the healthy branch. The sweet smell of its living flesh sticks in my nose. It was healthy to its core. I yelled for my dad to stop pulling when I saw its torsion and heard its creaking, but it was too late. We sat listening to it, and talking over it, until it all came down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had first tried pulling the dead branch by one of the down-hanging limbs, but it broke twice before we could get it out. So we got the long painting ladder and I climbed. I was greeted by that feeling, fainter than it was as a kid, of something hidden in its branches. Its arms kept me safe from falling while I chained up the dead branch. I worried that its removal would damage my tie-off branch, a beautiful fresh-looking offshoot four inches in diameter, and I planned to climb back up to the spot afterward to check on it. The spot was its parent branch, sixteen inches in diameter, soon to be shorn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unbeknownst to my parents, at some point during the extraction procedure I began directing a short film, positioning them to get the right angles, asking for particular shots. After it fell I crouched next to the shattered yellow bits and wept, and my mental edits went in another direction. Then I wept all the more because I couldn’t sort out whether I was crying more for the tree as a tree or for the tree as a memento mori.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brother’s enthusiasm redeemed the event, his calls for a treehouse, reminding us that the swing remains, and putting it to use while I tried to capture something that was already gone. The tree’s still here, and we’re still here, for a while more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I needed to portray all of that, and I edited obsessively until I had, and I showed it to everyone involved and people I love and they all loved it, and I felt empty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The post-publishing blues? In part, and I anticipate it again later today when I post this essay. Appropriately so. Creating something, a film, an essay, a child, is going to be a sunk cost. Inevitably. No matter what positive reactions come from it, it’ll never match the energy the creator puts into it. Call it the law of creative thermodynamics. But there was something more to the emptiness this time, a realization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any claim to creative primacy is nonsense. Creativity is a human quality. All humans are creative and should create, and art comes from all sorts of minds. Different sorts of minds produce different sorts of art, and a part of the realization that I’ve been trying to sort through this last week is the way that various approaches to art are attempting to do the same thing: realism, surrealism, hyperrealism, romanticism, impressionism, expressionism, etc., etc., are all trying to translate one kind of reality into a form consumable in another kind of reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are better seeds of hope. I shouldn’t balance stigma with aggrandizement; I should find what’s beautiful in the variety of human creation. Humans must differ. It creates strife, but it also creates—everything. Our creativity comes out of our confrontation with irregularities. Our minds are really good, when we let them, at sorting through those irregularities and coming up with something new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, whether more or less, I do have a different relationship to pain and beauty than some people do, and it introduces a problem for my attempt to express an artistic realism, a disconnect that sharpened that emptiness I felt the other day. If my sensitivity to an event produces a response that isn’t produced for others, then using realism in my portrayal of the event doesn’t communicate what I experience. One way to overcome that communication barrier is by translating. If my experienced reality is conceptually lurid, painting in lurid colors instead of the expected palette. If everywhere I look I see the capitalistic manipulation of sheeplike masses, approaching film editing with a Brechtian montage. It isn’t that these kinds of creators necessarily perceived drastically different qualia in their everyday lives, it’s that they met the mismatch by ramping up their presentation. That means, though, that even if I manage to communicate what I feel, it is only a translation; my realism remains buried. But why do I feel like I owe realism anything? What is it I want? For any human who desires to communicate their realism, I want it to be understood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Translation is necessary for understanding, and literary translation is an art form itself. There are translations that arguably outreach their original. Translations that stick to the original too closely often fail to communicate, while more extreme renderings offer us dazzling looks at reality, with the translation superimposed over the original. The translation takes into account the context of the author, the translator, and the reader, and those who do it best create something that can’t be created any other way. These translations become a new piece of reality themselves, and in the same way, what was once shocking in the modernist starkness and post-modernist irreverence is now just life. This essay employs styles that would have been taken as unreal two centuries ago, and this film is carefully edited to compress time to communicate what the raw footage didn’t show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point after I finished, posted, and screened the film, I felt disappointed in myself that I hadn’t gone for a more polished audio track in my post-production work; shouldn’t I have made it easier to listen to? It’s what I trained to do; why wouldn’t I give the viewer a slick, compressed, noise-gated experience? But in fact, I had labored for hours to produce the audio track as it currently stands. I had an original artistic vision to preserve the feel and sound of the experience as I experienced it, which was messy, at times hard to understand (I couldn’t tell what my dad said about my tie-off branch, and I still can’t tell in the recording), and saturated with nuanced ambient Oakley, Idaho sound, some of which I called out in my subtitles. So why had I insisted on this vision? Why didn’t I translate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At its best or its worst, a translation is not the original. Of course some originals are themselves translations, but these layers eventually get back to a root of lived experience, the only original thing. In order to get to the lived experience of another, at a certain point there’s a new step to take. You need to learn a new language. It never occurred to me before this week what is lost in my artistic translations, and in all extra-real art: the creator’s actual experience of the real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essay is an attempt to pile on additional layers of realism to the realism of the film, to communicate more of it by slowly adding the context it lacks, the context that moved me to create it in the first place. It’ll be reasonably argued that this is just another translation, that all art is mediated, that reality in isolated real-time pieces is boring, that it doesn’t sell, it doesn’t communicate, it doesn’t engage, and it doesn’t have a place in our over-, under-, hyper-translated modern culture. But who else wants to get to the root of it, the boring and the beautiful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about something more immediate? Reality in the original?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">Metaphors aren’t hard to come by when you’ve pulled down more of a tree than you meant, but they feel even closer when you’re the one who chose the spot to affix the chain, and then affixed it. I could really dig into those metaphors, compare them to my own slash-and-burn history, my tendency to break things open in order to know how they got put together, to hurt when I mean to heal, but right now I just want to talk about the tree.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Socialism</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/on-socialism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Socialism" /><published>2016-02-22T18:19:01+00:00</published><updated>2016-02-22T18:19:01+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/on-socialism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/on-socialism">&lt;p&gt;It’s important to me to attempt to keep my writing politically ambivalent, but I obviously skew to the left. Can I call myself a moderate Leftist? Not to be cute or tricky, but as a statement of a social and economic ambiguity that we should all examine? I acknowledge my conservative upbringing, and I’m glad to understand that perspective so intimately, but I have found more inclusive ideas across the political and economic spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/portland-business-district.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A city skyline over a river at dusk&quot; title=&quot;Portland business district, from the other side of the river&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought of myself as a socialist for some time, and have gotten pushback, for good reasons; there have been egregious failures among humanity’s economic social experiments. But I don’t believe in social experiments, and I don’t believe in sudden bloody revolution, whatever my sympathies to Marxist writing. I believe in slow revolutions&lt;!--more--&gt;, in the gradual tendency of society toward certain positions, in an implicit democracy of ideas. Of course sometimes the distribution of ideas is grossly unequal, and sometimes the corrections are not so gradual, even violent. I can’t say whether these reactive changes are necessary, but it’s easy to see that they then produce their own reactions, often resulting in oscillation in the short term. Much like market dynamics, when viewed on a larger time scale those oscillations are seen as only incremental changes on a more gradual trend line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s one aspect of socialism I want to focus on, so I don’t want to get too far into a general defense, but I’ll offer a summary for my purposes here: Socialism ≠ Leninism.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:leninism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:leninism&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Socialism ≠ Marx’s socialist mode of production.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:socialist-mode-of-production&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:socialist-mode-of-production&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Both are examples of socialist ideas, but socialism is broader than either.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:types-of-socialism&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:types-of-socialism&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There are many&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:many&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:many&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; examples of successful socialist programs. We depend on them. Debate that as you will, but I think it’s irresponsible to ignore the debt modern society owes to these ideas, just as it’s irresponsible to ignore the benefits we’ve gained from market economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one aspect I want to focus on, then, is this tendency to equate all types of socialism with the historical failures of particular socialist enterprises. It’s more than a tendency; it’s a tactic of big business proponents and big government opponents to throw pink sheets over socially progressive figures and call them ghosts, a la McCarthy. I most recently saw it in a social media post that linked Bernie Sanders with Soviet failures, by quoting a Sanders interview where he questions the necessity of “23 underarm spray deodorants or of 18 different pairs of sneakers”. The implication, of course, being that any lull in our orgy&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:orgy&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:orgy&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of competitive marketing will lead us to Soviet-level dearth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Context is important. In the interview leading up to the statement, Sanders was asked&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If the changes that you envision in tax policy, in finance, breaking up the banks, were to result in a more equitable distribution of income, but less economic growth, is that trade-off worth making?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And his full reply:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yes. If 99 percent of all the new income goes to the top 1 percent, you could triple it, it wouldn’t matter much to the average middle class person. The whole size of the economy and the GDP doesn’t matter if people continue to work longer hours for low wages and you have 45 million people living in poverty. You can’t just continue growth for the sake of growth in a world in which we are struggling with climate change and all kinds of environmental problems. All right? You don’t necessarily need a choice of 23 underarm spray deodorants or of 18 different pairs of sneakers when children are hungry in this country. I don’t think the media appreciates the kind of stress that ordinary Americans are working on. People scared to death about what happens tomorrow. Half the people in America have less than $10,000 in savings. How do you like that? That means you have an automobile accident, you have an illness, you’re broke. How do you retire if you have less than $10,000, and you don’t have much in the way of Social Security?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:sanders&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:sanders&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t vetted any of those numbers, which might be an essay for someone else. Indeed, I think socialism still has a lot to prove, but I do think it’s proving it. This also isn’t an unqualified endorsement of Sanders or his policies, or lack thereof, especially on non-economic social issues such as racial inequality. Again, though, I want to address this specific argument, because I think it’s bigger than the current election cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sanders was obviously being facetious about the deodorant and sneakers. His point wasn’t that we have too much selection. He wasn’t saying that the market, or competition within the market, is bad. He was saying that things like the legal requirement to maximize profit&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:duty-to-shareholder-value&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:duty-to-shareholder-value&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; is bad. He’s saying that the free market, left completely free, makes bad social choices. Companies do clever things with zero (or negative) social value, as long as it results in good quarterly reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s mix Smith and Levinas: while the invisible hand implies invisible faces, Sanders wants to restore the face-to-face encounter,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:face-to-face&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:face-to-face&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; to factor people more heavily into the equation. There are entrepreneurs who do this, but it’s not the default position of our economy. Indeed, as Shkreli&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:shkreli&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:shkreli&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has been fond of pointing out, sometimes it’s illegal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people put an emphasis on individualism at all costs, but then defend an economics that completely removes the individual. Socialists like Sanders want it the other way around. To see humanity as a social group with complex dynamics that ought not be ignored or isolated, but to be negotiated simultaneously. To then make visible, and account for, the material needs of each individual within the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where society’s economic sensibility is trending. It’s socialism, and it isn’t scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:leninism&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Often equated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/State_socialism&quot;&gt;State socialism&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:leninism&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:socialist-mode-of-production&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Similar to the above; that is, Lenin’s state socialism was a poor (and incomplete) implementation of this: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialist_mode_of_production&quot;&gt;Socialist mode of production&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:socialist-mode-of-production&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:types-of-socialism&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Types_of_socialism&quot;&gt;Types of socialism&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:types-of-socialism&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:many&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Many is a terrible word to use in a persuasive essay, but this particular “many” is standing in for a large amount of side research that can be done. I cringe to link you to a Daily Kos article because I have to provide so many caveats (this article is self-righteous, condescending, hyperbolic toward the end of the list, etc.) that it almost defeats the purpose of using it, but it’s the most comprehensive list I could find in a single place, and might serve as a starting point for further research (and/or rebuttal). It also depends on the broader view of socialism introduced above, so that can be left out of the rebuttals. The best rebuttals to this are probably the libertarian zero-government private-market solution arguments, although I disagree with most of those arguments. Although, to rebut my rebuttal rebuttal, I wouldn’t mind seeing some of these programs trimmed, especially the first one. And of course many of them are guilty of inefficiency that wouldn’t fly in the free market. Nevertheless, here is a summary of the “many”, many of which you undoubtedly benefit from in one way or another: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailykos.com/story/2012/3/29/1078852/-75-Ways-Socialism-Has-Improved-America&quot;&gt;75 Ways Socialism Has Improved America&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:many&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:orgy&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;A sensationalist choice of words that I’ll blame it on reading that Daily Kos article. And it makes for good marketing.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:orgy&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:sanders&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cnbc.com/2015/05/26/10-questions-with-bernie-sanders.html&quot;&gt;10 questions with Bernie Sanders&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:sanders&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:duty-to-shareholder-value&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“…the law requires corporate directors and managers to pursue long-term, sustainable shareholder wealth maximization in preference to the interests of other stakeholders or society at large…” &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2015/04/16/what-are-corporations-obligations-to-shareholders/a-duty-to-shareholder-value&quot;&gt;A Duty to Shareholder Value&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:duty-to-shareholder-value&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:face-to-face&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Face-to-face_(philosophy)&quot;&gt;Face-to-face (philosophy)&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:face-to-face&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:shkreli&quot;&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;A take that skews to the left: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/morning-mix/wp/2015/09/23/pharma-bro-martin-shkreli-and-the-very-american-debate-over-maximizing-profit/&quot;&gt;‘Pharma bro’ Martin Shkreli and the very American debate over maximizing profit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;And to the right: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/matthewherper/2016/01/20/solving-pharmas-shkreli-problem/&quot;&gt;Solving Pharma’s Shkreli Problem&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:shkreli&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">It’s important to me to attempt to keep my writing politically ambivalent, but I obviously skew to the left. Can I call myself a moderate Leftist? Not to be cute or tricky, but as a statement of a social and economic ambiguity that we should all examine? I acknowledge my conservative upbringing, and I’m glad to understand that perspective so intimately, but I have found more inclusive ideas across the political and economic spectrum. I’ve thought of myself as a socialist for some time, and have gotten pushback, for good reasons; there have been egregious failures among humanity’s economic social experiments. But I don’t believe in social experiments, and I don’t believe in sudden bloody revolution, whatever my sympathies to Marxist writing. I believe in slow revolutions</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thanksgiving</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/thanksgiving" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thanksgiving" /><published>2015-11-26T20:48:53+00:00</published><updated>2015-11-26T20:48:53+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/thanksgiving</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/thanksgiving">&lt;p&gt;I walked to a park to write this. The wind and the cold require me to write in heavy strokes to keep the ink flowing; the ink casts a shadow on the page before it dries. Today is as I imagined it. Solitary, but connected. Looking forward and back to more direct connection, and celebrating the connection inherent in community celebration. A family has their dinner set up in the pavilion, and a homeless man yells for a while in a Tom Waits preacher voice. A couple walks by, and with the sun at their backs creating shadow cowls, I thought they were a pair of nuns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/portland-park-bench.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Park bench with neighborhood homes in the background&quot; title=&quot;Horizon&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanksgiving Day tends to center around family, and I’m glad it does. Friendsgiving isn’t new, but it’s in style this year, and in some ways it’s a better celebration; family is the idea of embracing, and there’s more to give than thanks.&lt;!--more--&gt; I decided to spend much of today alone. It feels good but weird. Is my solitude honest, or am I like the voluntarily homeless who can return to a warm home when they feel like it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had an abundance of family celebrations; it’s why this was my favorite holiday growing up. Still, I’ve always hated sitting around a table taking turns expressing gratitude. Today, spending the day alone, separated from the weight of expression, I’ve tried to figure out why, aside from the general distaste for obligatory goodness. My concentric reasoning centered on this: People I’m grateful for ought to already know it; if not, saying it today won’t repair my failure. If there’s value in the day’s namesake, it’s as a reminder to express gratitude every day, so that today doesn’t have to feel like a big deal that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a solitary Thanksgiving Day, sitting under a setting sun, almost at the horizon myself, feet buried in leaves, is there value in expressing gratitude to myself? It isn’t a matter of mere self-esteem; it would have to be gratitude for what I do for myself. Do I take care of myself? Do I give myself things to live for? Do I challenge myself, and do I answer the challenge? Do I start things that matter to me? Do I finish them? At the end of a day, do I stop to recognize what went well? Do I surround myself with people who make me feel more like me? Do I, every day, do these same kinds of things for other people? Do I give them reasons to feel gratitude?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horizon is the houses across the street. People are sitting under those roofs giving thanks and giving gratitude. The sun’s down, and it’s time to walk back to my horizon, to be better at both.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">I walked to a park to write this. The wind and the cold require me to write in heavy strokes to keep the ink flowing; the ink casts a shadow on the page before it dries. Today is as I imagined it. Solitary, but connected. Looking forward and back to more direct connection, and celebrating the connection inherent in community celebration. A family has their dinner set up in the pavilion, and a homeless man yells for a while in a Tom Waits preacher voice. A couple walks by, and with the sun at their backs creating shadow cowls, I thought they were a pair of nuns. Thanksgiving Day tends to center around family, and I’m glad it does. Friendsgiving isn’t new, but it’s in style this year, and in some ways it’s a better celebration; family is the idea of embracing, and there’s more to give than thanks.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goose Summer</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/goose-summer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goose Summer" /><published>2015-11-21T20:34:50+00:00</published><updated>2015-11-21T20:34:50+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/goose-summer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/goose-summer">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/southern-idaho-rain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Brown grass in the foreground; rainy hills in the distance; two orange-capped posts&quot; title=&quot;Points&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nostalgia represents loss of the past, but it’s also loss in itself. The feeling, like a memory but more compact, is instantaneous and then gone. I’m left grasping, trying to expand the feeling into an actual memory, something to hold on to.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But often there is no memory, no event on the other side. Just a moment coupled with another moment, two points in time connected by neural gossamer.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gossamer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gossamer&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just now the other moment was at home in Oakley, around Thanksgiving or Halloween, in the kitchen or the laundry room, humid from cooking or laundering, and my mother is nearby, and that’s it. It’s gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gossamer&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“Middle English &lt;em&gt;gos(e)somer(e&lt;/em&gt;, apparently &amp;lt; &lt;em&gt;goose n.&lt;/em&gt; + &lt;em&gt;summer n.&lt;/em&gt;… The reason for the appellation is somewhat obscure. It is usually assumed that &lt;em&gt;goose&lt;/em&gt; in this compound refers to the ‘downy’ appearance of gossamer. But it is to be noted that German &lt;em&gt;mädchen-&lt;/em&gt; , &lt;em&gt;altweibersommer&lt;/em&gt; mean not only ‘gossamer’, but also a summer-like period in late autumn, a St. Martin’s summer; that the obsolete Scots &lt;em&gt;go-summer n.&lt;/em&gt; had the latter meaning; and that it is in the warm periods of autumn that gossamer is chiefly observed. These considerations suggest the possibility that the word may primarily have denoted a ‘St. Martin’s summer’ (the time when geese were supposed to be in season: compare German &lt;em&gt;Gänsemonat&lt;/em&gt; ‘geese-month’, November), and have been hence transferred to the characteristic phenomenon of the period.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gossamerer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gossamerer&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gossamer&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gossamerer&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;“gossamer, n. and adj.” OED Online. Oxford University Press, September 2015. Web. 21 November 2015.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gossamerer&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">Nostalgia represents loss of the past, but it’s also loss in itself. The feeling, like a memory but more compact, is instantaneous and then gone. I’m left grasping, trying to expand the feeling into an actual memory, something to hold on to.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kansas</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/kansas" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kansas" /><published>2012-11-21T00:03:16+00:00</published><updated>2012-11-21T00:03:16+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/kansas</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/kansas">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/kansas-fields.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;overlooking clusters of circular fields, from high above, toward a distant, blue horizon&quot; title=&quot;Terrestrial clouds&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flying over Kansas. The circles of harvested crops congregate like clusters of terrestrial clouds. A shallow reservoir interrupts a sad little stream, and it must look to me the way my writing looks to the universe or the gods, whichever is looking.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plains are flat except for cerebral wrinkles carrying other streams of thought, or just standing as empty memories. Here and there small towns are wedged, castles in the clouds, hopes of great ideas, redirecting the flow of water to feed and quench their population. Still other streams look like the signature of a great penman, or maybe the oh-so-lucid lines of an artist’s pen before a nude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In time the clouds become ordered, the elements compressed into square wafers, houses and sheds adorning most squares, turning the patchwork into a great silicon circuitboard, calculating whether or not millions will eat or not, live or die. They don’t show, though, the people inside the solder-houses, the farmers and their families investing millions of dollars and fourteen hours a day most days to till, plant, and harvest those circles and squares, to plan the rotation and fret the broken wheel line or pivot, to wake early and work in the cold and wet, to sleep late after kneeling before a temperamental God beside wife and children, all to give eldest daughter straight teeth and a good education so that she can grow up to be a lawyer or a writer or a mom, or all three, rarely returning home to central Kansas but always bringing with her the love of a larger machine than can be seen from the solder, and a wilder weather system than can be seen from within a single cloud.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">Flying over Kansas. The circles of harvested crops congregate like clusters of terrestrial clouds. A shallow reservoir interrupts a sad little stream, and it must look to me the way my writing looks to the universe or the gods, whichever is looking.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Something New</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/something-new" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Something New" /><published>2012-09-23T23:05:27+00:00</published><updated>2012-09-23T23:05:27+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/something-new</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/something-new">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/something-new.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A new shoot of green in a bed of brown leaves&quot; title=&quot;An idea crossing the threshold. Rock Canyon, June 2010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that it is unlikely that I will ever write anything totally new. Most of what I write is novel to me, and synthesized by me, which is why I find it worth recording at all, but there have been uncounted generations far more intelligent who have surely at some point beat me to the ideas.&lt;!--more--&gt; When I come across examples of victors in this subtle competition, though, I am encouraged and feel honored that I should be in the company of such greats. I also feel then like I am on the right track toward a novel discovery of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also recognize this pattern in the writings of others. Sometimes it is between writers in the same school of thought, contemporary to each other; other times the pattern is seen across eras, or between two people that likely didn’t have access to each other’s works. Still, somehow the ideas coalesce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think what I am trying to get at here is something like Dawkins’s meme (see, even this idea about novelty that I’m expressing itself isn’t entirely novel). Someone may come up with a completely new and ground-breaking idea, but it only enters the consciousness, the idea sphere of a few people. The idea is then internalized and slowly disseminated through the newly-expressed ideas of those few people, perhaps unconsciously. Several iterations later, after many mutations, the sphere grows, until finally the idea may emerge from someone who has no affiliation or contact with the originator but who has far greater access to the public, and the idea then becomes common knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, there is a threshold somewhere between nascent, novel ideas and pervasive public consciousness, and there must be some calculable mean of the number of iterations and mutations before that threshold is crossed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the recording and publishing of new-to-you concepts is a critical part of really changing the world with ideas, perhaps even more important than the origination of the idea, or at least as important, especially because it is often impossible to differentiate between the two, and because it is the repeaters, the churners, the re-interpreters that will tip the idea over that threshold mean.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">I know that it is unlikely that I will ever write anything totally new. Most of what I write is novel to me, and synthesized by me, which is why I find it worth recording at all, but there have been uncounted generations far more intelligent who have surely at some point beat me to the ideas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Name, Rank, and Serial Number</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/name-rank-and-serial-number" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Name, Rank, and Serial Number" /><published>2012-09-08T00:09:21+00:00</published><updated>2012-09-08T00:09:21+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/name-rank-and-serial-number</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/name-rank-and-serial-number">&lt;p&gt;People who like to read literature, when they talk, like to talk about who they read at least as much as what they read. The what is why we read, but the who, all of them, are woven into our conversations like trophies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/name-rank-serial-number.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Handwritten copy of some of this piece's text&quot; title=&quot;Who you are reading&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could just talk about the ideas separated from the names, and the conversations would function just as as well, but we never do. The trading-card exchange of names is a territorial dance of sorts&lt;!--more--&gt;, or perhaps the name, rank, and serial number of the academic world. When names are given in common, they serve as pass phrases to some elite society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one holds a card the other does not, it establishes an ad hoc two-level hierarchy, with one ruling over the other. The ruler feels either superiority or an excitement to share something new—perhaps both in some—that accelerates their pace and increases their self-confidence. The ruled feels not just regret over not knowing the name, but a larger sort of academic guilt or incompetence, sensing that if there is this one name not on their shelf, there is likely a whole section of the repertoire that they have failed to assimilate. The ruled reacts to this incompetence with excitement to learn, feigned disinterest, or non-commital noddings, followed by a later cursory internet search and the appearance of having known all along.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">People who like to read literature, when they talk, like to talk about who they read at least as much as what they read. The what is why we read, but the who, all of them, are woven into our conversations like trophies. We could just talk about the ideas separated from the names, and the conversations would function just as as well, but we never do. The trading-card exchange of names is a territorial dance of sorts</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Youth: Then vs. Now</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/youth-then-vs-now" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Youth: Then vs. Now" /><published>2012-08-04T00:47:27+00:00</published><updated>2012-08-04T00:47:27+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/youth-then-vs-now</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/youth-then-vs-now">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We degenerate into hideous puppets, haunted by the memory of the passions of which we were too much afraid, and the exquisite temptations that we had not the courage to yield to. Youth! Youth! There is absolutely nothing in the world but youth!&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:nothing&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:nothing&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/unripe-peach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An unripe peach, still on the tree&quot; title=&quot;Young peaches, in the orchard behind our house&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would religion preach against youthful indulgence? Perhaps because abstinence has given a few the impression of a quietly happy or satisfactory life—I can’t begrudge them that. I also don’t deny that indulgence often leads to excess and extremes, which are dangerous, if still useful.&lt;!--more--&gt; And the worship of or clinging to youth is really just another form of betrayal against the present. The grass is not greener ten years ago, but it could have been had I recognized then the value of the present, and can be now if I do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I just ate a peach, washed and sliced. The yield of the bitten peach, the sweetness of the flesh and bitter bite of the skin, the juice between fingers—they are sensations of summers past, memorial bouquets, and it is probably as much the fault of the nostalgia as it is the eating that make it my favorite fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it is, it must be, the eating that makes the fruit so great; if it weren’t the nostalgia wouldn’t exist, and if I don’t sow seeds in present soil I’ll have nothing to harvest next year when I hunger for the past. And when next year comes, and that hunger drives me to crush a peach slice against the roof of my mouth, I had better be sure to lay up in store that sensation against future winters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it isn’t youth that we should treasure, but now. Anything that robs us of the present or of presence, that is what sin is. Sin has almost exclusively been spoken of in a religious context, as a divine rule broken. Might we instead use this law of perceived existence in time and space as its pivot? Dishonesty, idleness, addiction, vanity; being inconsiderate, marring the natural world, killing a man—these are the deadly sins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are able to enjoy the presence of fruits in the present better than we could those of the past. We can enjoy tomorrow’s better if we savor today’s. And the best peach is the one that, yesterday, was a day away from falling to the ground, and that today sits on my tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What was youth at its best? A green, an unripe time…&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:unripe&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:unripe&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:nothing&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Oscar Wilde, &lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; (Three Sirens Press, New York, 1931), 34&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:nothing&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:unripe&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;ibid., 243&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:unripe&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">We degenerate into hideous puppets, haunted by the memory of the passions of which we were too much afraid, and the exquisite temptations that we had not the courage to yield to. Youth! Youth! There is absolutely nothing in the world but youth!1 Why would religion preach against youthful indulgence? Perhaps because abstinence has given a few the impression of a quietly happy or satisfactory life—I can’t begrudge them that. I also don’t deny that indulgence often leads to excess and extremes, which are dangerous, if still useful. Oscar Wilde, The Picture of Dorian Gray (Three Sirens Press, New York, 1931), 34&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Oceans &amp;amp; Albums</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/oceans-albums" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Oceans &amp; Albums" /><published>2012-07-27T23:28:00+00:00</published><updated>2012-07-27T23:28:00+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/oceans-albums</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/oceans-albums">&lt;p&gt;The first time I saw the ocean, she owned me. It was an encounter bigger than the moment, bigger than the steps that had led me, by way of a marriage altar, to that rocky Washington coast. Much bigger than any of the pictures, narrations, or melodies that had previously been, to me, the ocean. Its dimensions threatened my cognitive abilities and exhausted my mind in its efforts to take it all in. It was like looking into a great box, one that I couldn’t see far enough into, whose sides and top I could never hope to see, whose corners I was certain hid secrets I needed to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/washington-coast.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Rocky coast, very small figure on a rock out in the water&quot; title=&quot;I am that speck, sitting on the far rock, staring out into the abyss. Photo taken by Rachel Dorothy Anderson, June 2006&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understood, then, why all the paintings, stories, and songs existed; I knew then that humanity has, for millennia, looked at this body as we now look at the deep reaches of space. I have since breathed the salty air from several locations, and have come to see&lt;!--more--&gt; her&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:her&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:her&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; as one great thing, differing in temperament from one place and time to the next, but cohesive in identity. I know, on some small scale, the character of that hidden soul of whom Melville wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To really know a soul takes a lot of time, over many miles. With enough time one can predict moods and finish sentences. Mind reading is really just knowing enough about the person, their experiences, habits, preferences; with enough of that context you can empathize to a prophetic degree. It’s how lovers know each other, and how mariners know the sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What? you cry, All that through the medium of context? A key, both to the heart and to whatever treasure chests of knowledge we find waiting in those hidden corners? I dare say yes. Understanding what role is played by context, both our own and that of the people with whom and things with which we interact, will unlock the keys of the kingdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I speak of context I mean a handful of things, so I suppose I should offer you what I see as the context of that context. Everything we have learned and experienced in life is spun together somewhere upstairs into a fabric or filter that influences everything that passes through it. When we read a new book, we aren’t getting only the words of a writer sitting in his or her underwear in a dark room pounding furiously or scratching absently in front of an inked sheet of paper or a ghastly grid of pixels. In addition to all that glory we get intimations of ideas harvested from the last thing we read, and the dozens of things before. Camus lives next door to Thoreau’s shack; Darwin inadvertently capsizes Noah’s ark; Suzanne Collins has the unfortunate burden of bunking with Bradbury. In every case the former is illuminated by the latter and vice versa; sometimes favorably, sometimes critically. More often, no value judgment is made since the act of connecting these ideas and filtering each one in terms of the rest is both subconscious and constant. Whether you are aware of it or not your brain is making all of these connections, and when you read together the two words “red dress” you not only conjure up images of red objects and various styles of dresses, your mind also bridges the two data points and makes all sort of inferences regarding what type of creature generally inhabits a dress, and (depending on the cut of the dress and shade of red your mind settled on) the nature, personality, and perhaps even hair color, figure, and sexual activity of the creature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it is with everything we consume. Literature, film, music, art, religion, politics, sports, conversations, food, smells; traveling, running, skiing, surfing, fishing, boating: The larger the net we cast, the more meaning we catch. In a very literal and physiological way, the more we experience in life, the more we are able to see of it in the future. It’s an exponential experience involving the continual linking and relinking of neurons and the sparking of complex electrical impulses along those chains, the chains being in fact the threads that comprise the previously mentioned filtering fabric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of this is something we’ve been slowly realizing over the last few hundred years: that meaning is subjective, that all we are really able to know is what we think and what we see,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:goddess&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:goddess&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and that the twentieth-century modernist’s absolute world wasn’t the way we interacted with that knowledge. Modernism yielded to post-modernism, a reactive era with inherently nebulous boundaries. Knowledge was deferred, truth was relative, the color red was whatever each person’s experience told them it was. The musicologist Lawrence Kramer has provided one of my favorite observations of postmodernism, that it “treats as emancipatory the principle that subjectivity is… ‘culturally constructed.’”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kramer&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kramer&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This gave us pop art and culture, a fusion in architecture of modernist aesthetics and classical idioms, and in music, a wave of popular forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What began in the music houses of Tin Pan Alley has increased many-fold and resulted in a final triumph of popular or folk music over art music. Academics and lovers of classical music can wail about that assessment, but contemporary composers, for the most part, have held to a narrow view of art music largely contingent upon the very modernist ideas of Schoenberg and his school, while a very vibrant music evolved and grew up around them, burying them under meters of rich undergrowth comprised of jazz, rock, hip-hop, MTV, music videos, Madonnas, affected Brahmsian film scores, EPs, LPs, and CDs. Albums. Stacks and stacks of albums. The symphony, once the greatest of large forms, is now hidden behind the shadows of cities built out of columns and heaps of magnetic tape, cardboard-sheathed vinyl, and laser-etched plastic. The still-intricate symphony has not died, but it is merely a museum in a metropolis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time records were made out of shellac instead of vinyl, and they spun approximately 78 times every minute, much faster than the later standardized 33 1/3 RPM, meaning that these early discs only allowed for three to four minutes of recorded sound, depending on the diameter. In addition to standardizing the typical song length for popular music, this format, when packaged together in back-to-back sheathes similar to a photo album, was dubbed a “record album” and used to distribute works that were longer than a few meagre minutes, such as orchestral suites, operas, and symphonies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the materials and methods used were improved upon, the speeds could be reduced, the discs consolidated, and more ear candy stuffed into more grooves. Record producers and publishers saw a new opportunity: If we get a hot artist to record one or two hits, we can then fill the rest of the black with two or three lower quality, cheaper to produce songs. They then charged customers for all half-dozen or so of the tracks, seeing that they would buy the whole thing on the strength of the hits. Those higher-quality songs were then released to radio networks one at a time and called “singles”, stretching out the commercial viability of the album over a much longer period of time than if they had merely released them all simultaneously. Where customers had once paid for two three-minute songs fueled by their brief appearance on stage or on film, they now bought four, six, ten songs, possibly also driven by shows or movies, but with frequent reminders over the hi-fi, re-excited every few months by the appearance of a new single from the same album. A drastic growth in sales was inevitable. It is why a music industry exists today, and healthily, in spite of its complaints about recession and piracy.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:riaa&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:riaa&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the following years, two peculiar things happened to our dubious hero, the album: it transcended its commercialist fetters; it became commercially obsolete. The two appear to be similar, and point toward one redeeming end, but they came about independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first, commercial transcendence, was due to the efforts of artists in the 60s and 70s who saw in it something greater than a vehicle for singles. The advent of the concept album in the hands of the The-bands and British-invaders bled into the concept-album-obsessed prog-rockers, who perfected the idea and set the stage for my personal favorite offerings from the alt-rockers, goth-gazers, and grungers of the following two decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second, commercial obsolescence, was the fault of that great enemy of the music industry: digital music. In retrospect, the RIAA’s railings against peer-to-peer music sharing probably had less to do with piracy than it did with their realization that their carefully placed profit bucket was being superseded by the ability for consumers to sip their music one track at a time, paying just for what they wanted and avoiding the less-well-crafted filler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so the fairytale has reached a crucial point. Many in the industry have declared the album dead, and it is, from their perspective. At the same time, serious musicians recognize the holistic power of the album, and continue to compose in that format. From its pragmatic beginnings, the record album has fully escaped commercialism. It is now poised to be solely an artistic form, a vehicle not for profits but for the greater meaning that can come from several smaller works presented in a single context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the point in an essay where it would be poetic to reintroduce the opening concept; in this case, a trillion-something cubic meters of water. With that in mind, I’ll cut over to the latest pelagic experience in my life. Last month, The Smashing Pumpkins (alt-rock, prog-rock, The-band, shoegaze, goth, grunge) released their first album in five years, and their best in perhaps ever.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:chill&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:chill&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It’s called &lt;em&gt;Oceania&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Billy Corgan and his band, in its various incarnations, have been kind to the album as a form. The thirty-track&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:track-count&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:track-count&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;Mellon Collie&lt;/em&gt; of the mid-nineties not only immortalized them but also reintroduced the massively-scoped concept album to a new generation of long-haired kids who had missed it the first time around. While their first two records were extremely tight, they really found something new with this one. The tone and subject matter evolved in their later work, but this approach to writing albums continued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivering this newest album took some introspection and exorcising. Billy released three LPs between the demise of the original band at the turn of the century and this; all three stand on their own but weren’t enough to keep out the sharks. The world moved on from the old band, but Billy wasn’t done. In 2005, on the day he released a viscerally, beautifully personal (and poorly received) solo offering, he abruptly announced his intention to reform the Pumpkins. Bridges had been burned, and so the only original band member was Jimmy Chamberlin, the drummer; the rest he cobbled together from his various connections. The resulting music was good. It was really good. But again, the critics dismissed it, and Billy became increasingly bitter toward the industry, his fickle fans, and his long-time love affair with the album. And so he rather petulantly moved on without any of them. “We’re done with the record business,” he said.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kot-done&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kot-done&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In concerts he openly provoked fans and challenged their apathy, rejecting what he saw as their desire to be puppet-masters of a has-been rock band. In interviews he groused about the state of the industry and played the part of a victim, further alienating him from his fan base. In response to all of this he was asked, “So ‘Zeitgeist’ was the last album?” to which he replied&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We’re done with that. There is no point. People don’t even listen to it all. They put it on their iPod, they drag over the two singles, and skip over the rest. The listening patterns have changed, so why are we killing ourselves to do albums, to create balance, and do the arty track to set up the single? It’s done.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kot-really-done&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kot-really-done&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was heartbreaking to hear. One of the great champions of the album declared it dead. It looked, for some time, like a captain had abandoned his ship. Music was made, and again, much of it was good. The message was that they were now constructing a super-album, but if there was a concept, it didn’t coalesce into anything like their former works. The music was released one track at a time, for free. A bold move commercially, but artistically, the songs barely floated. Flotsam, deprived of structural strength. Each of them isolated, suspended on a thin surface, cresting waves and following currents to an unknown shore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The band toured. It was slightly different now; Billy insisted it was the strongest it had ever been. When they took the stage with a new lineup, a stripped-down presentation, and a set list comprised of these piece-songs, these album-seeds, something happened. The songs grew. A garden of tears, Billy called it. A kaleidoscope. In their collocation, colors emerged that hadn’t been there before, overtones of meaning. I remembered why I loved the band. And apparently, so did Billy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We basically sat down and said, ‘This is it. This is boring.’ So what do we do to actually change this? Only thing that made sense was to make an album. Can you make an album that is so strong that it reignites the flame within you and the audience? Is that even culturally possible?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:kot-oceania&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:kot-oceania&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He decided to find out. Billy wiped the sea-spray from his eyes and commanded his newly-crewed vessel to new waters, ostensibly somewhere between Indonesia and Hawaii. He marketed it as an album-within-an-album. He promised to return to his old form, to craft like he used to craft. The journey took over a year, and the sharks and storms were no less present, but they finally arrived. A week before the album’s release date, the band announced via email that the entire work would be freely available for straight-through listening until its official release, “allowing the album to be heard as it was intended to be.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:straight-through&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:straight-through&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Billy emphasized that the band&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;was dead set on making an album where every song was just as valuable as any other, ignoring the typical claptrap you hear about needing a single.  The only way to make the case that every song on &lt;em&gt;Oceania&lt;/em&gt; is worth hearing is to put your heart into the sequence as a cohesive whole.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cohesive-whole&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cohesive-whole&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They got it. My heart sighed an audible Finally! when I read this. With this incantation they were at last free to create the modern large-scale musical work not because of corporate prescriptions but because it best served the art of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following my own snobbish tradition I didn’t listen through the album until I received my copy on vinyl. Music often sounds better on vinyl than it does digitally; as an analog medium it represents sound with infinitely greater resolution than any digital format can. The actual audible difference depends on how the music was originally recorded, how it was mastered before pressing, and, of course, on the ear of the listener, as well as how well the record has been cared for. The real reason for this tradition, though, is not because of the analog advantage; it is because of how it influences my perception in inaudible ways. It is well established in the culinary world that color directly adds to the experience we call flavor; in the same way, the flavor of an album is affected by the format in which it is consumed. Again, when the context changes (no matter how slight) so does the meaning, and with it the perceived enjoyment. Many dismiss the preference for vinyl because of the nominal tangible gains;&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:tangibility&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:tangibility&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I acknowledge the dismissal, but continue to choose the medium for the way it demands attention and encourages the listener to leave behind the day for a consecrated hour of sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/oceania.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A vinyl copy of Oceania, playing, label slightly blurred&quot; title=&quot;A tradition of spinning&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first hour with this particular sound was emotional. I heard a band again, not just a lone man with an old name. When I heard female backup vocals and checked the jacket to find the new bass player Nicole’s name bearing vocal credits, I nearly wept. The whole experience was like embracing an old friend. Track after track, flipping the disc every three or four, a story unfolded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve listened to the album at least seven times since.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:seven&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:seven&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The second time around was a more energizing experience, although that might have had something to do with the listening setting, mowing the lawn with my head wrapped in my Beyerdynamic phones, the sounds punctuated by quasi-quixotic battles between the can of Raid in my hand and the early-summer explosion of the wasp population. The difference in mastering between the digital and the vinyl also affected that second listen; the vinyl mastering was much warmer and saturated, possibly contributing to the more nostalgic experience of the first listen, but also adding some distortion to those troublesome inner tracks. The digital lost some of that warmth, but gained a crispness that paid off well in the higher-tempo portions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Oceania&lt;/em&gt; is a joy. Each song bears the love of careful artistry, but it is only in their union that we can appreciate what they do; only together can they tell their story. I could have heard “Quasar” alone and felt glad for its &lt;em&gt;Siamese Dream&lt;/em&gt;–like opening, but also feared that Billy had finally resorted to pandering to his hit-song-craving fans. As the opening track to an entire album, however, I felt the gladness but never had the chance to fear, because I was immediately treated with so many other subtleties of Pumpkin past: the Mellotron in “Celestials” harkening back to &lt;em&gt;Mellon Collie&lt;/em&gt;; the ghost of D’arcy’s backups on several tracks; the effervescent lead guitar in “Pinwheels” and “Wildflower”, straight out of &lt;em&gt;TheFutureEmbrace&lt;/em&gt;; a Zwan-ish vibe in “The Chimera”. Onto those echoes are summed new sounds for the Pumpkins: the rhythm acoustic guitar sprinkled throughout, something we’ve rarely heard from Billy except for on demos; an expansive use of sine-wave synths, a brighter alternative to the many squares and saws in &lt;em&gt;Adore&lt;/em&gt;; a dramatic switch to double-time in “The Chimera”, no doubt a contribution of the new drummer, Mike; a deeply layered female-vocal harmony on the bridge of “Pinwheel”, a stunning new aesthetic for them, and one of many on that track. Any of those facts taken from any of those recordings on their own would have resulted in the same confusion that the one-song-at-a-time release schedule was giving us before. It wasn’t that those tracks weren’t doing new things, or giving nods to yesterdays, it’s that none of them had the strength of any of the rest for support. As it is we have a remarkable work—for all the nuances above, perhaps their finest—an ocean of ideas, differing in temperament from one track to the next, but cohesive in meaning, with many a secret buried in its depths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I saw the ocean was in San Diego. The city is dirty, but it supports much more palatable suburbs. The trim, welcoming town of Coronado boasts the highest-rated beach in the nation.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:dr-beach&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:dr-beach&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The water is cold, but the sand shimmers, and the ocean banters with the sun much as she does at any set of coordinates she claims on this spinning sphere. It was a brisk day for June, and I didn’t stay to visit as long as I’d have liked. We exchanged small-talk, Salacia and I; she got me a cup of tea, which I sipped absent-mindedly. We stared together, past the gamboling half-naked fellow ocean lovers, at the subject of our adoration. It was a good moment, spent in silence, yearning to drink it all up without being drowned. There is so much of life out there, and while this one spot is lovely, and precious for the glimpse it affords of her plutonic heart, I want to gaze more deeply. I want the bigger picture, the zooming-out, the true world view. I want a larger-than-world view; I want to know the world from every angle, top to bottom, forward and backward in time; I want to look out past the horizon and discern that vaster ocean, the light-years of history branded on the face of space-time, ever fed into our eyes like magnetized acetate running past a tape head, tape so old and brittle that the encoding substance disintegrates into memory the moment it is observed and recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is so much, and music seems more trivial than quadrivial. However, none of us are capable of cognizing the so-much. We can search and scratch and horde, but the scope of reality is unbounded. While we can’t consume it all, we can frame what we do consume in as comprehensive a matte as we can construct.  Learning is an additive process, after all. It directly inherits from this notion of contextual meaning since learning is merely meaning, compounded. I once read an idea&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:silverman&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:silverman&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that further augmented my understanding of the way we learn (thereby proving itself); it was that we can’t fully understand or interact directly with a facet of reality until we have a way of representing it. By this principle, the individual who looks to the humanities for as many representations of the ocean as the mind can hold may, by virtue of our continual contextual learning, come to understand her better than those who have walked a small stretch of her shores but neglected her many depictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we listen to songs, how are we listening to them? If on the radio, our understanding of their meaning is filtered through a fabric of advertisement, radio-personality gimmicks, and perhaps the roar of traffic. If from a playlist or in a random shuffle from our digital player, the meaning becomes one that we have subjectively created by our particular choice in music. I’m not making an indictment of either of those methods; in fact, the latter has particular value because of how it allows us to hand-pick the meaning of a song, in fact creating new meaning for it by the songs we place around it. James Brown’s “I Feel Good” means one thing when surrounded by Katrina and the Waves and Johnny Nash, and a completely different thing than it does grooving next to The Meters and El Michels Affair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, let’s assume that the music you are listening to comes from an artist who deliberately packages a song with a dozen others, each of them created especially to complement the rest. There is no better kind of music than that which is the product of careful planning or unifying energy, and when either or both of those things are involved, what you get is a killer album. If that effort and spirit has been invested and manifested in this &lt;em&gt;gestalt&lt;/em&gt;, shouldn’t we want that added meaning? It’s like a hidden track that you can’t get to by playing past the end; the historical subtext of a century-old novel; the “third something” of Eisenstein’s films.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:eisenstein&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:eisenstein&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Please, continue to love the single songs, just as we love ocean-side vacation spots, but do what you can to know the whole soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/coronado.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Looking out at the horizon over cresting coastal waves&quot; title=&quot;In which the lady offered me a spot at her table. Coronado Beach, June 2012&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:her&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There’s a risk in personifying an inanimate object, and a greater risk at assigning it a gender. (It’s a shame that English lacks a gender-neutral way of personifying matter. Not for long, perhaps.) Criticisms of female personfication generally have something to pay attention to, especially if it’s a male doing the personifying. Having acknowledged that, the ocean must be personified, and it is, perhaps in a real sense, our first mother. More personally, while I prefer to dissolve their binary association and to emphasize the similarities between men and women over the exaggerated differences, there is something about the experience of someone of a gender other than our own that we’ll never be able to apprehend, in the same way that I’ll never be able to know all of the ocean.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:her&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:goddess&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;More on this in a &lt;a href=&quot;/goddess-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;previous essay&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:goddess&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kramer&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Lawrence Kramer, &lt;em&gt;Classical Music and Postmodern Knowledge&lt;/em&gt; (Berkeley, University of California Press, 1995), 21&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kramer&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:riaa&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The RIAA’s 2011 Year-End Shipment Statistics reports a .2% growth from its 2010 report; unfortunately for them they reported this growth even as they were claiming industry-wide losses as a justification for passing SOPA.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:riaa&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:chill&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Calm down, all of you who just unsheathed swords; I’m about to explain.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:chill&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:track-count&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Closer to 60 if you count all of the (outrageously good) B-sides from The Aeroplane Flies High, a box-set of singles from Mellon Collie. Mind-boggling for a band’s 3rd album.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:track-count&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kot-done&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Billy Corgan, interview by Greg Kot, “Billy Corgan dishes on the Smashing Pumpkins: The past is dead to me”, Chicago Tribune, December 9, 2008, accessed July 3, 2012, &lt;a href=&quot;http://leisureblogs.chicagotribune.com/turn_it_up/2008/12/billy-corgan-di.html&quot;&gt;http://leisureblogs.chicagotribune.com/turn_it_up/2008/12/billy-corgan-di.html&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kot-done&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kot-really-done&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ibid.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kot-really-done&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:kot-oceania&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Billy Corgan, interview by Greg Kot, “Billy Corgan’s mission statement for ‘Oceania’: Do or die”, Chicago Tribune, June 15, 2012, accessed July 6, 2012, &lt;a href=&quot;http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2012-06-15/entertainment/ct-ae-0617-billy-corgan-20120615_1_d-arcy-wretzky-siamese-dream-bjorn-thorsrud&quot;&gt;http://articles.chicagotribune.com/2012-06-15/entertainment/ct-ae-0617-billy-corgan-20120615_1_d-arcy-wretzky-siamese-dream-bjorn-thorsrud&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:kot-oceania&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:straight-through&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Email message to the band’s mailing list on June 11, 2012&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:straight-through&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cohesive-whole&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ibid.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cohesive-whole&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:tangibility&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Although one of the greatest advantages of the medium is its very tangibility: When the world ends and all your batteries have died, I’ll have built a gramophone and will be bathing in Led Zeppelin’s IV.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:tangibility&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:seven&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Chicago Tribune 2012, op. cit.: “Don’t expect anyone to listen seven times.”&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:seven&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:dr-beach&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;That is, if you can trust the analysis of someone who calls himself &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.drbeach.org/&quot;&gt;Dr. Beach&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:dr-beach&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:silverman&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Not a new one, but here represented by Kaja Silverman talking about the ideas of Pierce. &lt;em&gt;The Subject of Semiotics&lt;/em&gt; (Oxford University Press, 1983), 16&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:silverman&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:eisenstein&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;He wrote that, when assembling two strips of film, “no matter how unrelated they might be, and frequently despite themselves, they engendered a ‘third something’ and became correlated when juxtaposed according to the will of an editor.” Sergei M. Eisenstein, &lt;em&gt;The Film Sense&lt;/em&gt;, trans. Jay Leyda (New York: Harcourt, Brace and Company, 1947), 9&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:eisenstein&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">The first time I saw the ocean, she owned me. It was an encounter bigger than the moment, bigger than the steps that had led me, by way of a marriage altar, to that rocky Washington coast. Much bigger than any of the pictures, narrations, or melodies that had previously been, to me, the ocean. Its dimensions threatened my cognitive abilities and exhausted my mind in its efforts to take it all in. It was like looking into a great box, one that I couldn’t see far enough into, whose sides and top I could never hope to see, whose corners I was certain hid secrets I needed to know. I understood, then, why all the paintings, stories, and songs existed; I knew then that humanity has, for millennia, looked at this body as we now look at the deep reaches of space. I have since breathed the salty air from several locations, and have come to see</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goddess of Knowledge</title><link href="http://kylealanhale.com/goddess-of-knowledge" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goddess of Knowledge" /><published>2012-06-07T05:31:19+00:00</published><updated>2012-06-07T05:31:19+00:00</updated><id>http://kylealanhale.com/goddess-of-knowledge</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://kylealanhale.com/goddess-of-knowledge">&lt;p&gt;As I write I am witnessing, first-hand, the transit of Venus across the sun. It isn’t very often that a person can truly learn something new, and know that it is true when before it had only been believed. I now know that there exists a solid body between the Earth and the Sun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/transit-of-venus-notes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photograph of notebook pages, with sketch of transit&quot; title=&quot;Drawing the transit made me feel very 17th-century.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or do I? What have I really learned here? What do I know now that I didn’t before? It isn’t a new question. Humanity has been wondering what it means to know something since nearly as long as we have known how to write down what we know.&lt;!--more--&gt; An entire field of study has emerged around the topic. The opinions range widely, along a scale whose notches indicate degrees of skepticism. By even asking this question I am placing myself closer to the skeptical end of the spectrum, perhaps near our friend Camus, whose skepticism proved to be ultimately, ironically, and tragically appropriate. He had this to say on knowledge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Of whom and of what indeed can I say: ‘I know that!’ This heart within me I can feel, and I judge that it exists. This world I can touch, and I likewise judge that it exists. There ends my knowledge, and the rest is construction. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:camus&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:camus&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of what indeed, indeed. While Venus has been worshipped for several things, today I looked to her for knowledge, for something new of which I can say that thing. What I learned was this: When I looked at the sun through filtered glasses, or at a projection through a telescope, there was a black, round dot superimposed on a bright white disc, the former being approximately 100 times smaller than the latter, or somewhere in that order of magnitude. I know that other black dots were visible within the disc, much smaller. In the next hour or so when the clouds clear up I am predicting that I will verify the claims of many bright minds that the larger black dot will move with respect to the smaller ones, toward the edge of the disc. Once I witness that, it will be the conclusion of my knowledge concerning the thing. I will not know what any of the black dots are; for that matter, I will not really know what is that burning white disc in the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest—the nature of the sun, the orbit of Venus, not to mention her composition, distance, fitness (or lack thereof) for terraformation, age, annual rainfall,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:rip&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:rip&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; etc.—all come to me by the way of second-hand accounts. Constructions, as the translator of Camus put it. I say I know them because of the exhaustedly repeated and vetted observations of others, not to mention the many recordings in various forms that I can myself consume—but when I say that I know these things, what I’m really saying is that I trust all of them as facts: I believe in them, and I believe those who profess them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, is that different from the claims of religion? In terms of repeatability and universal verifiability, sure, but on a fundamental epistemological plane, the experience is identical: one man believes the words and experiences of another. Many religious people have seen their own black dots in front of white discs, and have then proclaimed knowledge of heavenly things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, though, two differences that are important to me. First, the nature of Venus has been observed and recorded by countless individuals for thousands of years. The building of knowledge from generation to generation has worked, well enough that we now capture enough data on the spots of light that were once thought to be stars that we can create visual representations of that data to show that they are actually entire galaxies. There is a flip side to that accretion of knowledge, however; it at the same time has given us wild, nearly incomprehensible theories of atomic structure,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:truthfulness&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:truthfulness&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; the evidence of which only the elect few can claim to be able to observe. Are they any different from prophets?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, and more important to me, I have never had the spiritual equivalent of what I have empirically witnessed today. The religious tell me that that is the function of some spiritual being who will confirm truths to me, generally in the form of some sort of spiritual emotion. It isn’t the place for this short treatment to go into the challenges around trusting our fickle (although important) human emotions, so I will be content to say that I do not trust emotions as a compass to truth or true living. Okay, then, the religious would persist, It is a matter of faith. Some things are not meant to be known. Perhaps that is true, but consider the alternative way of living: I no longer have to merely believe the words of others when they speak of a solid planet called Venus that is between us and the sun; I now know that something is there. I still have to believe and trust that their calculations are correct that led them to say that that black dot is the same bright wanderer I see at night, but I now have even more of a reason to believe that portion. I have no such sign in religion, I only have the testimonies of others, testimonies that compete with still others’, and sometimes even contradict themselves. These inconsistencies could merely be the fault of humans, granted; if so, where is the consistent god that I can observe as I have this goddess?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:conversation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:conversation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/media/transit-of-venus-projection.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Photograph of transit projection, sunspots visible&quot; title=&quot;Projected with a cheap thrift-store telescope onto a white surface; captured with camera phone. Note the visible sunspots to the left of Venus, the darkest dot.&quot; style=&quot;float: right; margin: 0 0 0 1em; width: auto;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my efforts to track the movement of the small dot in relationship to the smaller dots, I have fought wind and clouds and the rotation of the earth itself. I have chased the sun to the top of a barn in the orchard behind my house, scurrying up the tapering fruit ladders leaning against it with telescope and notebook under arm, and here I now sit, watching a lovely orange-cream clouded sunset. I was able to get a few more convincing glimpses of the coy Venus, now obviously further along her transit, the darker of the sunspots visible to her left. What a glorious era it is that I, alongside millions of other lowly humans, can project her silhouette, record the image with a device that fits in my pocket, and then climb down from my perch, enter my home, and corroborate what I recorded against the video feed that NASA is supplying from atop a mountain in Hawaii. That, dear world, is knowledge, constructed or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:camus&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Camus, The Myth of Sysiphus&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:camus&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:rip&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;RIP, Bradbury&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:rip&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:truthfulness&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I am making no statements here on the truthfulness of these theories; true or not, science’s current ideas on particles are fascinating.&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:truthfulness&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:conversation&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goddess-of-knowledge-conversation&quot;&gt;Some additional conversation on these points&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:conversation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&amp;#65038;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Kyle Alan Hale</name></author><summary type="html">As I write I am witnessing, first-hand, the transit of Venus across the sun. It isn’t very often that a person can truly learn something new, and know that it is true when before it had only been believed. I now know that there exists a solid body between the Earth and the Sun. Or do I? What have I really learned here? What do I know now that I didn’t before? It isn’t a new question. Humanity has been wondering what it means to know something since nearly as long as we have known how to write down what we know.</summary></entry></feed>